Guide to the Records of the Research Institute for the Study of Man (RISM) Medical School Attitude Questionnaire (MSAQ) RISM.RG.7
New York University Archives
Records of the Research Institute for the Study of Man (RISM) Medical School Attitude Questionnaire (MSAQ)
1958-1960
New York University Archives
Rubin, Vera D.
Research Institute for the Study of Man
RISM.RG.7
4.5 Linear Feet in 6 boxes
Conducted between 1959 and 1960, the Medical Students Attitude Questionnaire was a cross-cultural study undertaken by the Research Institute for the Study of Man (RISM) and the World Federation on Mental Health, which examined the beliefs and feelings medical students had toward a variety of issues pertaining to their future roles as medical professionals. The materials include correspondence, questionnaires, and responses.
Arrangement note
This collection has been arranged in three series chronologically:
Series
Series I: Pretesting Correspondence
Series II: Research/Working Papers
Series III: Completed Questionnaires
Biographical/Historical note
Founded in 1955, the Research Institute for the Study of Man (RISM) is a non-profit organization that promotes and carries out multidisciplinary and cross cultural studies on topics of contemporary relevance. In 1959, a study was undertaken by RISM and the World Federation on Mental Health to understand the attitudes that medical students of all specialties and from around the world had towards issues of mental health in medicine.
Participants were asked about their feelings towards the salience of social and emotional factors in illness, their tolerance for handling cases where social and emotional problems complicated the medical problems, their attitudes towards diagnosing what falls within the scope of mental illness and the impact of social biases in diagnosing therapy. Questions regarding their personal backgrounds, their preferred specialties, stereotypes towards specialties and what environment they wanted to practice medicine in were also part of the questionnaire.
The questionnaire was administered to students in many parts of the world, including Austria, Belgium, Canada, Chile, France, Germany, Great Britain, Mexico, Peru, the Philippines, and the United States.
Access Restrictions
The Collection contains human subject data, and some material may be restricted. Please contact the University Archives for questions about restricted material.
Related Archival Materials note
Vera D. Rubin Papers, RISM RG 1 Research and Training Program for the Study of Man in the Tropics Records of the RISM Bolivia Project Records of the Puerto Rico Study RISM Vertical Files RISM Guide to Records of the Interuniversity Consortium
Scope and Contents note
The records of the Medical School Attitude Questionnaire (MSAQ), part of the collection on the Research Institute on the Studies of Man, consist of 4.5 linear feet of material from 1959-1960. The collection has been broken into three series: Pretesting Correspondence, Research and Working Papers, and Questionnaires.
Series I: Pretesting Correspondence and Questionnaire Drafts contains correspondence regarding the content and development of the questionnaire as well as copies of the drafts with comments, pretests and official copies of the completed questionnaire. It is arranged by subject.
Series II: Research and Working Papers contains copies of questions and data from previous studies used as reference in the development of the MSAQ and is grouped by subject.
Series III: Questionnaires contains a bulk of the contents and is comprised of completed questionnaires by medical students from universities around the world and some blank copies of the questionnaires. The questionnaires have been grouped by the part of the world or specific institution where they were completed.
Separated Materials note
No materials have been removed from the collection.
Questionnaires.; South America.; Philippines.; Perú.; Canada.; Chile.; Vienna (Austria); Dental students.; Mental health.; Medical students.; México.; Germany.; Great Britain.; Brussels (Belgium).; London (England).; Correspondence.; Paris (France); France.; Rubin, Vera D.; McGill University; Seton Hall University; Brandeis University
- Series I: Pretesting Correspondence, 1959-1960
  - Medical School Attitude Questionnaire (MSAQ) pretesting correspondence, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - MSAQ pretesting correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - MSAQ pretesting correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Dr. Vera Rubin personal correspondence, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - MSAQ Purpose (copy), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Questionnaire draft, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Questionnaire pretest draft, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Official Questionnaire, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Official Questionnaire, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Columbia University Study of Internships and Residencies (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series II: Research/Working Papers, 1959
  - Checklist and Project Descriptions, 1958-1960
  - MSAQ for Mexico, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Mental Health Questionnaire Working Papers, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Mental Health Questionnaire Working Papers, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Sample Questions from other studies, 1956-1959 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Series III: Questionnaires, 1959-1960
  - Incoming Students questionnaire drafts, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Graduating Students questionnaire drafts, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Completed Questionnaires-Postgraduate Center, McGill University, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Completed Questionnaires-Postgraduate Center, McGill University, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Completed Questionnaires-Postgraduate Center, McGill University, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Completed Questionnaires-Postgraduate Center, McGill University, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Completed Questionnaires-Postgraduate Center, McGill University, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Postgraduate Center for Psychotherapy Questionnaire Introduction, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Completed Questionnaires-Postgraduate Center, McGill University, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Completed Questionnaires-Postgraduate Center, McGill University, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Completed Questionnaires-Postgraduate Center, McGill University, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Completed Questionnaires-Postgraduate Center, McGill University, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Completed Questionnaires-Peru, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Completed Questionnaires-Mexico, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Completed Questionnaires-Philippines, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Completed Questionnaires-South America, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Completed Questionnaires-Paris, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Completed Questionnaires-London, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Completed Questionnaires-United Kingdom, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Completed Questionnaires-France, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Blank Questionnaires, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Blank Questionnaires, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Blank Questionnaires, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Blank Questionnaires, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Blank Questionnaires, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Completed Questionnaires-Dental Students, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Completed Questionnaires-Dental Students, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Completed Questionnaires-Dental Students, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Completed Questionnaires-Brandeis University, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Completed Questionnaires-Seton Hall University, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Completed Questionnaires-Seton Hall University, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Completed Questionnaires-Germany, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Completed Questionnaires-Brussels, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Completed Questionnaires-Vienna, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 6)